<Chapter Label="Free inverse semigroups">
  <Heading>Free inverse semigroups</Heading>

  This chapter describes the functions in &GAP; for dealing with
  free inverse semigroups.<P/>

  A <E>free inverse semigroup</E> is an inverse semigroup having the following
  universal property. More precisely, <M>S</M> is a free inverse semigroup
  on a non-empty set <M>X</M> if <M>F</M> is an inverse semigroup with a map f
  from <M>F</M> to X such that for every inverse semigroup S and a
  map g from X to S there exists a unique morphism g' from FS to S
  such that fg' = g. This object is unique up to isomorphism.
  Moreover, by the universal property, every inverse
  semigroup can be expressed as a quotient of a free inverse
  semigroup. For more details see... <P/>

  The internal representation of free inverse semigroup elements uses
  Munn tree diagrams. [JDM reference the chapter of the main GAP manual about
  inverse semigroups, partial perms, free groups and semigroups]. 
  
  For more information regarding free inverse semigroups and the Munn
  representations see <Cite Key = "howie"/>. [JDM more specific.]
  
  For a free inverse semigroup element there is a canonical form
  given by specifying a set M of maximal group-reduced left factors
  of the given element. Then for each element w of M, there is an
  idempotent ww^-1 and the product of these idempotents multiplied
  by group-reduced word gives the canonical form. If the free
  inverse semigroup element is described in terms of Munn
  tree diagrams, maximal group-reduced left factor is just the shortest
  path from the start vertex to a leaf. Similarly group-reduced 
  word is the shortest path from start vertex to the terminal vertex.
  See <Cite Key="howie"/> <P/>. [JDM: reference the man section about
  CanonicalForm].

  [JDM: printing and a shortest word representing, include explanation/example
  that this does not give a canonical form.]

  <Section Label = "Free inverse semigroups">
  <Heading> Free inverse semigroups</Heading>
</Section>
  <#Include Label = "FreeInverseSemigroup">

  <Section>
    <Heading>Operators and operations for free inverse semigroup elements
    </Heading>
    <List>
<Mark><C><A>w</A> ^ -1</C></Mark>
<Item>
  returns the semigroup inverse of the free inverse semigroup element <A>w</A>.
</Item>

<Mark><C><A>u</A> * <A>v</A></C></Mark>
<Item>
  returns the product of two free inverse semigroup elements <A>u</A>
  and <A>v</A>.
</Item>
</List>

  <#Include Label = "CanonicalForm"> 
</Section>
</Chapter>
