<TitlePage>
  <Title>&Semigroups;</Title>
  <Version>Version &VERSION;</Version>

  <Author>J. D. Mitchell
    <Email>jdm3@st-and.ac.uk</Email>
    <Homepage>http://www-groups.mcs.st-andrews.ac.uk/~jamesm/</Homepage>
  </Author>

  <Author>Stuart Burrell</Author>
  <Author>Manuel Delgado</Author>
  <Author>James East</Author>
  <Author>Attila Egri-Nagy</Author>
  <Author>Nicholas Ham</Author>
  <Author>Julius Jonu&#353;as</Author>
  <Author>Markus Pfeiffer</Author>
  <Author>Chris Russell</Author>
  <Author>Ben Steinberg</Author>
  <Author>Finn Smith</Author>
  <Author>Jhevon Smith</Author>
  <Author>Michael Torpey</Author>
  <Author>Wilf A. Wilson</Author>

  <Copyright>&copyright; &COPYRIGHTYEARS; by J. D. Mitchell et al.<P/>
    &Semigroups; is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the <URL Text = "GNU General Public License">
    http://www.fsf.org/licenses/gpl.html</URL> as published by the Free Software
    Foundation; either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later
    version.
  </Copyright>

  <Abstract>
    The &Semigroups; package is a &GAP; package containing methods for
    semigroups, monoids, and inverse semigroups.  There are particularly
    efficient methods for semigroups or ideals consisting of transformations,
    partial permutations, bipartitions, partitioned binary relations,
    subsemigroups of regular Rees 0-matrix semigroups, and matrices of various
    semirings including boolean matrices, matrices over finite fields, and
    certain tropical matrices.
    <P/>

    &Semigroups; contains efficient methods for creating semigroups, monoids,
    and inverse semigroup, calculating their Green's structure, ideals, size,
    elements, group of units, small generating sets, testing membership,
    finding the inverses of a regular element, factorizing elements over the
    generators, and so on. It is possible to test if a semigroup satisfies a
    particular property, such as if it is regular, simple, inverse, completely
    regular, and a variety of further properties.
    <P/>

    There are methods for finding presentations for a semigroup, the
    congruences of a semigroup, the normalizer of a semigroup in a permutation
    group, the maximal subsemigroups of a finite semigroup, smaller degree
    partial permutation representations, and the character tables of inverse
    semigroups. There are functions for producing pictures of the Green's
    structure of a semigroup, and for drawing graphical representations of
    certain types of elements.
  </Abstract>

  <Acknowledgements>
    I would like to thank P. von Bunau, A. Distler, S. Linton, C. Nehaniv,  J.
    Neubueser, M. R. Quick, E. F. Robertson, and N. Ruskuc for their help and
    suggestions.  Special thanks go to J. Araujo for his mathematical
    suggestions and to M. Neunhoeffer for his invaluable help in improving the
    efficiency of the package.
    <P/>

    Stuart Burrell contributed methods for checking finiteness of semigroups of
    matrices of the max-plus and min-plus semirings.<P/>

    Manuel Delgado and Attila Egri-Nagy contributed to the function
    <Ref Oper = "DotString"/>.<P/>

    James East, Attila Egri-Nagy, and Markus Pfeiffer contributed to the part of
    the package relating to bipartitions. I would like to thank the University
    of Western Sydney for their support of the development of this part of the
    package.
    <P/>

    Nick Ham contributed many of the standard examples of bipartition
    semigroups.
    <P/>

    Julius Jonu&#353;as contributed the part of the package relating to free
    inverse semigroups, and contributed to the code for ideals.
    <P/>

    Zak Mesyan contributed to the code for graph inverse semigroups; see Chapter
    <Ref Chap="GraphInverseSemigroups"/>.<P/>

    Markus Pfeiffer contributed the majority of the code relating to
    semigroups of matrices over finite fields.
    <P/>

    Yann P&#233;resse and Yanhui Wang contributed to the attribute
    <Ref Attr = "MunnSemigroup"/>.<P/>

    Jhevon Smith and Ben Steinberg contributed the function
    <Ref Attr = "CharacterTableOfInverseSemigroup"/>.<P/>

    Michael Torpey contributed the part of the package relating to congruences.
    <P/>

    Wilf A. Wilson contributed to the part of the package relating maximal
    subsemigroups and smaller degree partial permutation representations of
    inverse semigroups. We are also grateful to C. Donoven and R. Hancock for
    their contribution to the development of the algorithms for maximal
    subsemigroups and smaller degree partial permutation representations.
    <P/>

    We would also like to acknowledge the support of: EPSRC grant number
    GR/S/56085/01; the Carnegie Trust for the Universities of Scotland
    for funding the PhD scholarships of J. Jonu&#353;as and W. Wilson when they
    worked on this project; the Engineering and Physical Sciences Research
    Council (EPSRC) for funding the PhD scholarship of M. Torpey when he worked
    on this project (EP/M506631/1).
  </Acknowledgements>

</TitlePage>
