<TitlePage>
  <Title>&Citrus;</Title>
  <Subtitle>Computing with Semigroups of Transformations and Partial
    Permutations</Subtitle>
  <Version>Version &VERSION;</Version>

  <Author>J. D. Mitchell
    <Email>jdm3@st-and.ac.uk</Email>
    <Homepage>http://tinyurl.com/jdmitchell</Homepage>
  </Author>

  <Copyright>&copyright; &COPYRIGHTYEARS; by J. D. Mitchell.<P/>

    &Citrus; is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under
    the terms of the <URL Text="GNU General Public License">
    http://www.fsf.org/licenses/gpl.html</URL> as published by the Free Software
    Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later
    version.

  </Copyright>

  <Abstract>
     The &Citrus; package is a &GAP; package for computing with semigroups of
     transformations and partial permutations. Citrus contains more efficient
     methods than those available in the GAP library (and in many cases more
     efficient than any other software) for creating semigroups of
     transformations and partial permutations, calculating their
     Green's classes, size, elements, group of units, minimal ideal,
     small generating sets, testing membership, finding the inverses of
     a regular element, and factorizing elements over the generators, and
     many more. It is also possible to test if a semigroup  satisfies a
     particular property, such as if it is regular, simple, inverse,
     completely regular, and a variety of further properties. Several
     catalogues of examples are provided, such as generators for the
     endomorphism monoids of every connected graphs with at most 8 vertices,
     and generators of the endomorphism monoids of the non-abelian groups with
     order at most 64.
  </Abstract>

  <Acknowledgements>
    I would like to thank P. von Bunau, A. Distler, S. Linton, J.  Neubueser,
    M. R. Quick, E. F. Robertson, and N. Ruskuc for their help and
    suggestions.  Special thanks go to J. Araujo for his mathematical
    suggestions and to M.  Neunhoeffer for his invaluable help in improving the
    efficiency of the package. <P/>

    I would also like to acknowledge the support of the Centre of Algebra at
    the University of Lisbon, and of EPSRC grant number GR/S/56085/01.
  </Acknowledgements>

</TitlePage>
