<Chapter Label = "McAlister triple semigroups">
  <Heading>
    McAlister triple semigroups and E-unitary inverse semigroups     
  </Heading>  
    In this section, we describe the functions in &GAP; for creating and
    computing with McAlister triple semigroups and their subsemigroups.
    This implementation is based on the section in Chapter 5 of
    <Cite Key = "Howie1995aa"/> but differs from the treatment in Howie
    by using right actions instead of left. Some definitions found in
    the documentation are changed for this reason. <P/>

    The importance of the McAlister triple semigroups lies in the fact that
    they are exactly the E-unitary inverse semigroups, which are an important
    class in the study of inverse semigroups. <P/>

    First we define E-unitary inverse semigroups. It is standard to
    denote the subsemigroup of a semigroup consisting of its idempotents by
    <C>E</C>. A semigroup <C>S</C> is said to be <E>E-unitary</E> if for all
    <C>e</C> in <C>E</C> and for all <C>s</C> in <C>S</C>:

      <List>
        <Item>
          <C>es</C> <M>\in</M> <C>E</C> implies <C>s</C> <M>\in</M> <C>E</C>,
        </Item>
        <Item>
          <C>se</C> <M>\in</M> <C>E</C> implies <C>s</C> <M>\in</M> <C>E</C>.
        </Item>
      </List>

    For inverse semigroups these two conditions are equivalent. We are only
    interested in <E>E-unitary inverse semigroups</E>. 
    Before defining McAlister triple semigroups we define a McAlister triple.
    A <E>McAlister triple</E> is a triple <C>(G,X,Y)</C> which consists of:

    <List>
      <Item>
        a partial order <C>X</C>,
      </Item>
      <Item>
        a subset <C>Y</C> of <C>X</C>,
      </Item>
      <Item>
        a group <C>G</C> which acts on <C>X</C>, on the right, by order
        automorphisms. That means for all <C>A,B</C> <M>\in</M> <C>X</C> and
        for all <C>g</C> <M>\in</M> <C>G</C>: <C>A</C> <M>\leq</M> <C>B</C> if
        and only if <C>Ag</C> <M>\leq</M> <C>Bg</C>.
      </Item>
    </List>

    Furthermore, <C>(G,X,Y)</C> must satisfy the following four properties to
    be a McAlister triple:

    <List>
      <Mark> M1 </Mark> 
      <Item>
        <C>Y</C> is a subset of <C>X</C> which is a join-semilattice together
        with the restriction of the order relation of <C>X</C> to <C>Y</C>.
      </Item>
      <Mark> M2 </Mark> 
      <Item>
        <C>Y</C> is an order ideal of <C>X</C>. That is to say, for all <C>A</C>
        <M>\in</M> <C>X</C> and for all <C>B</C> <M>\in</M>
        <C>Y</C>: if <C>A</C> <M>\leq</M> <C>B</C>, then <C>A</C> <M>\in</M>
        <C>Y</C>.
      </Item>
      <Mark> M3 </Mark> 
      <Item>
        Every element of <C>X</C> is the image of some element in <C>Y</C> moved
        by an element of <C>G</C>. That is to say, for every <C>A</C> <M>\in</M>
        <C>X</C>, there exists some <C>B</C> <M>\in</M> <C>Y</C> and there exists
        <C>g</C> <M>\in</M> <C>G</C> such that <C>A</C> = <C>Bg</C>.
      </Item>
      <Mark> M4 </Mark> 
      <Item>
        Finally, for all <C>g</C> <M>\in</M> <C>G</C>, the intersection
        <C>{yg : y </C><M>\in</M><C> Y}</C> <M>\cap</M> <C>Y</C> is non-empty.
      </Item>
    </List>

    We may define an E-unitary inverse semigroup using a McAlister triple. Given 
    <C>(G,X,Y)</C> let <C>M(G,X,Y)</C> be the set of all pairs <C>(A,g)</C> in
    <C>Y x G</C> such that <C>A</C> acted on by the inverse of <C>g</C> is in
    <C>Y</C> together with multiplication defined by <P/>

    <C>(A,g)*(B,h) = (Join(A,Bg^-1),hg)</C> <P/>

    where <C>Join</C> is the natural join operation of the semilattice and
    <C>Bg^-1</C> is <C>B</C> acted on by the inverse of <C>g</C>. With this
    operation, <C>M(G,X,Y)</C> is a semigroup which we call a <E>McAlister
    triple semigroup</E> over <C>(G,X,Y)</C>. In fact every McAlister triple
    semigroup is an E-unitary inverse semigroup and every E-unitary inverse
    semigroup is isomorphic to some McAlister triple semigroup. Note that there
    need not be a unqiue McAlister triple semigroup for a particular McAlister
    triple because in general there is more than one way for a group to act on
    a partial order.

  <Section>
    <Heading>
      Creating McAlister triple semigroups    
    </Heading>

    <#Include Label = "IsMcAlisterTripleSemigroup">
    <#Include Label = "McAlisterTripleSemigroup">
    <#Include Label = "McAlisterTripleSemigroupGroup">
    <#Include Label = "McAlisterTripleSemigroupPartialOrder">
    <#Include Label = "McAlisterTripleSemigroupSemilattice">
    <#Include Label = "McAlisterTripleSemigroupAction">
    <#Include Label = "IsMcAlisterTripleSemigroupElement">
    <#Include Label = "McAlisterTripleSemigroupElement">
  </Section>

</Chapter>
