<Chapter Label = "Free objects">
  <Heading>
    Free objects
  </Heading>

  This chapter describes the functions in &Semigroups; for dealing with free
  inverse semigroups and free bands. This part of the manual and the functions
  described herein were written by Julius Jonu&#353;as.<P/>

  <Section>
    <Heading>
      Free inverse semigroups
    </Heading>

    An inverse semigroup <M>F</M> is said to be <E>free</E> on a non-empty set
    <M>X</M> if there is a map <M>f</M> from <M>F</M> to <M>X</M> such that for
    every inverse semigroup <M>S</M> and a map <M>g</M> from <M>X</M> to
    <M>S</M> there exists a unique homomorphism <M>g'</M> from <M>F</M> to
    <M>S</M> such that <M>fg' = g</M>. Moreover, by this universal property,
    every inverse semigroup can be expressed as a quotient of a free inverse
    semigroup.
    <P/>

    The internal representation of an element of a free inverse semigroup
    uses a Munn tree. A <E>Munn tree</E> is a directed tree with distinguished
    start and terminal vertices and where the edges are labeled by generators so
    that two edges labeled by the same generator are only incident to the same
    vertex if one of the edges is coming in and the other is leaving the vertex.
    For more information regarding free inverse semigroups and the Munn
    representations see Section 5.10 of <Cite Key = "Howie1995aa"/>.
    <P/>

    See also <Ref Chap = "Inverse semigroups and monoids" BookName = "ref"/>,
    <Ref Chap = "Partial permutations" BookName = "ref"/> and <Ref Sect = "Free
      Groups, Monoids and Semigroups" BookName = "ref" />.
    <P/>

    An element of a free inverse semigroup in &Semigroups; is displayed, by
    default, as a shortest word corresponding to the element.  However, there
    might be more than one word of the minimum length. For example, if <M>x</M>
    and <M>y</M> are generators of a free inverse semigroups, then <Display>xyy
      ^ {-1}xx ^ {-1}x ^ {-1} = xxx ^ {-1}yy ^ {-1}x ^ {-1}.</Display> See <Ref
      Attr = "MinimalWord" Label = "for free inverse semigroup element"/>.
    Therefore we provide a another method for printing elements of a free
    inverse semigroup: a unique canonical form.  Suppose an element of a free
    inverse semigroup is given as a Munn tree. Let <M>L</M> be the set of words
    corresponding to the shortest paths from the start vertex to the leaves of
    the tree. Also let <M>w</M> be a word corresponding to the shortest path
    from start to terminal vertices. The word <M>vv ^ {-1}</M> is an idempotent
    for every <M>v</M> in <M>L</M>.  The canonical form is given by multiplying
    these idempotents, in shortlex order, and then postmultiplying by <M>w</M>.
    For example, consider the word <M>xyy ^ {-1}xx ^ {-1}x ^ {-1}</M> again.
    The words corresponding to the paths to the leaves are in this case
    <M>xx</M> and <M>xy</M>. And <M>w</M> is an empty word since start and
    terminal vertices are the same. Therefore, the canonical form is
    <Display>xxx ^ {-1}x ^ {-1}xyy ^ {-1}x ^ {-1}.</Display> See <Ref Oper =
      "CanonicalForm" Label = "for a free inverse semigroup element"/>.

    <#Include Label = "FreeInverseSemigroup">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeInverseSemigroupCategory">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeInverseSemigroup">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeInverseSemigroupElement">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeInverseSemigroupElementCollection">
  </Section>

  <Section>
    <Heading> Displaying free inverse semigroup elements </Heading>
    There is a way to change how &GAP; displays free inverse semigroup
    elements using the user preference <C>FreeInverseSemigroupElementDisplay</C>.
    See <Ref Func = "UserPreference" BookName = "ref"/> for more information
    about user preferences.<P/>

    There are two possible values for <C>FreeInverseSemigroupElementDisplay</C>:
    <List>
      <Mark>minimal </Mark>
      <Item> With this option selected, &GAP; will display a shortest word
        corresponding to the free inverse semigroup element. However,
        this shortest word is not unique. This is a default setting.
      </Item>

      <Mark>canonical</Mark>
      <Item> With this option selected, &GAP; will display a free inverse
        semigroup element in the canonical form.
      </Item>
    </List>

    <Example><![CDATA[
gap> SetUserPreference("semigroups",
>                      "FreeInverseSemigroupElementDisplay",
>                      "minimal");
gap> S := FreeInverseSemigroup(2);
<free inverse semigroup on the generators [ x1, x2 ]>
gap> S.1 * S.2;
x1*x2
gap> SetUserPreference("semigroups",
>                      "FreeInverseSemigroupElementDisplay",
>                      "canonical");
gap> S.1 * S.2;
x1x2x2^-1x1^-1x1x2]]></Example>
    </Section>

    <Section>
      <Heading>Operators and operations for free inverse semigroup elements
      </Heading>
      <List>
        <Mark><C><A>w</A> ^ -1</C></Mark>
        <Item>
          returns the semigroup inverse of the free inverse semigroup element
          <A>w</A>.
        </Item>

        <Mark><C><A>u</A> * <A>v</A></C></Mark>
        <Item>
          returns the product of two free inverse semigroup elements <A>u</A>
          and <A>v</A>.
        </Item>
        <Mark><C><A>u</A> = <A>v</A> </C></Mark>
        <Item>
          checks if two free inverse semigroup elements are equal, by comparing
          their canonical forms.
        </Item>
      </List>

      <#Include Label = "CanonicalForm">
      <#Include Label = "MinimalWord">
    </Section>

  <Section>
    <Heading>
      Free bands
    </Heading>

    A semigroup <M>B</M> is a <E>free band</E> on a non-empty set <M>X</M> if
    <M>B</M> is a band with a map <M> f </M> from <M> B </M> to <M>X</M> such that
    for every band <M> S </M> and every map <M> g </M> from <M>X</M> to <M> B </M>
    there exists a unique homomorphism <M> g'</M> from <M>B</M> to <M>S</M> such
    that <M>fg' = g</M>. The free band on a set <M>X</M> is unique up to
    isomorphism.  Moreover, by the universal property, every band can be expressed
    as a quotient of a free band.<P/>

    For an alternative description of a free band. Suppose that <M> X </M> is a
    non-empty set and <M> X ^ + </M> a free semigroup on <M> X </M>. Also suppose
    that <M> b </M> is the smallest congurance on <M> X ^ + </M> containing the set
    <Display> \{(w ^ 2, w) : w \in X ^ + \}. </Display> Then the free band on
    <M> X </M> is isomorphic to the quotient of <M> X ^ + </M> by <M> b </M>.
    See Section 4.5 of <Cite Key = "Howie1995aa" /> for more information on
    free bands.

    <#Include Label = "FreeBand">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeBandCategory">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeBand">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeBandElement">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeBandElementCollection">
    <#Include Label = "IsFreeBandSubsemigroup">
    <#Include Label = "ContentOfFreeBandElement">
    
  </Section>

  <Section>
    <Heading>Operators and operations for free band elements
    </Heading>
    <List>
      <Mark><C><A>u</A> * <A>v</A></C></Mark>
      <Item>
        returns the product of two free band elements <A>u</A>
        and <A>v</A>.
      </Item>
      <Mark><C><A>u</A> = <A>v</A> </C></Mark>
      <Item>
        checks if two free band elements are equal.
      </Item>
      <Mark><C><A>u</A> &lt; <A>v</A> </C></Mark>
      <Item>
        compares the sizes of the internal representations of two free
        band elements.
      </Item>
    </List>

    <#Include Label = "GreensDClassOfElement" >
  </Section>
</Chapter>
