<Chapter Label = "Semigroups and monoids defined by generating sets">
  <Heading>
    Semigroups and monoids defined by generating sets
  </Heading>

  In this chapter we describe the various ways that semigroups and monoids
  defined by generating sets can be created in &SEMIGROUPS;; where the
  generators are, for example, those elements described in earlier chapters of
  this manual.

  <Section Label = "Underlying algorithms">
    <Heading>Underlying algorithms</Heading>
    Computing the Green's structure of a semigroup or monoid is a fundamental
    step in almost every algorithm for semigroups.  There are two fundamental
    algorithms in the &SEMIGROUPS; package for computing the Green's structure
    of a semigroup defined by a set of generators. In the next two subsections
    we briefly describe these two algorithms.

    <Subsection Label = "Acting semigroups">
      <Heading>
        Acting semigroups
      </Heading>
      The first of the fundamental algorithms for computing a semigroup defined
      by a generating set is described in <Cite Key = "Mitchell2019aa"/>. When
      applied to a semigroup or monoid with relatively large subgroups, or
      &D;-classes, these are the most efficient methods in the &SEMIGROUPS;
      package.  For example, the complexity of computing, say, the size of a
      transformation semigroup that happens to be a group, is the same as the
      complexity of the Schreier-Sims Algorithm (polynomial in the number of
      points acted on by the transformations) for a permutation group.
      <P/>

      In theory, these algorithms can be applied to
      compute any subsemigroup of a regular semigroup; but so far in the
      &SEMIGROUPS; package they are only implemented for semigroups of:
      transformations (see <Ref Chap="Transformations" BookName="ref"/>),
      partial permutations
      (see <Ref Chap="Partial permutations" BookName="ref"/>),
      bipartitions (see Chapter <Ref Chap="Bipartitions and blocks"/>),
      matrices over a finite field
      (see Section <Ref Sect="Matrices over finite fields"/>);
      subsemigroups of regular Rees 0-matrix semigroups over permutation groups
      (see Chapter <Ref Chap="Rees matrix semigroups" BookName="ref"/>),
      and subsemigroups of McAlister triples (see Section <Ref Sect="McAlister
        triple semigroups"/>).
      <P/>

      We refer to semigroups to which the algorithms in
      <Cite Key = "Mitchell2019aa"/> can be applied as <E>acting semigroups</E>,
      and such semigroups belong to the category
      <Ref Filt="IsActingSemigroup"/>.<P/>

      If you know <E>a priori</E> that the semigroup you want to compute is
      large and &J;-trivial, then you can disable the special methods for
      acting semigroups when you create the semigroups; see Section <Ref Sect
        = "Options when creating semigroups"/> for more details.<P/>

      It is harder for the acting semigroup algorithms to compute Green's
      &L;- and &H;-classes of a transformation semigroup and the methods used
      to compute with Green's &R;- and &D;-classes are the most efficient in
      &SEMIGROUPS;.
      Thus, if you are computing with a transformation semigroup, wherever
      possible, it is advisable to use the commands relating to Green's &R;-
      or &D;-classes rather than those relating to Green's &L;-  or
      &H;-classes. No such difficulties are present when computing with the
      other types of acting semigroups in &SEMIGROUPS;.<P/>

      There are methods in &SEMIGROUPS; for computing individual Green's
      classes of an acting semigroup without computing the entire data
      structure of the underlying
      semigroup; see <Ref Oper = "GreensRClassOfElementNC"/>.  It is also
      possible to compute the &R;-classes, the number of elements and test
      membership in a semigroup without computing all the elements; see, for
      example, <Ref Meth = "GreensRClasses"/>, <Ref Attr = "RClassReps"/>, <Ref
        Oper = "IteratorOfRClasses"/>, or
      <Ref Attr = "NrRClasses"/>.  This may be useful if you want to study a very
      large semigroup where computing all the elements of the semigroup is not
      feasible.<P/>
    </Subsection>

    <#Include Label = "IsActingSemigroup">

    <Subsection Label="FroidurePin">
      <Heading>The Froidure-Pin Algorithm</Heading>
      The second fundamental algorithm for computing finite semigroups is the
      Froidure-Pin Algorithm <Cite Key = "Froidure1997aa"/>. The &SEMIGROUPS;
      package contains two implementations of the Froidure-Pin Algorithm: one
      in the &LIBSEMIGROUPS; C++ library and the other within the
      &SEMIGROUPS; package kernel module.<P/>

      Both implementations outperform the algorithms for acting semigroups when
      applied to semigroups with small (trivial) subgroups.  This method is
      also used to determine the structure of a semigroup when the algorithms
      described in <Cite Key = "Mitchell2019aa"/> do not apply. It is possible
      to specify which methods should be applied to a given semigroup; see
      Section <Ref Sect = "Options when creating semigroups"/>.<P/>

      A semigroup to which the Froidure-Pin Algorithm can be applied in
      &SEMIGROUPS; satisfy <Ref Prop="CanUseFroidurePin"/>.  Every acting
      semigroup in &SEMIGROUPS; satisfies <Ref Prop="CanUseFroidurePin"/>
      and the Froidure-Pin Algorithm is used to compute certain properties or
      attributes.
      <P/>

      Currently, the &LIBSEMIGROUPS; implementation of the Froidure-Pin
      Algorithm can be applied to semigroups consisting of the following types
      of elements: transformations (see <Ref Chap="Transformations"
        BookName="ref"/>), partial permutations (see <Ref Chap="Partial
        permutations" BookName="ref"/>), bipartitions (see Chapter <Ref
        Chap="Bipartitions and blocks"/>), partitioned binary relations (see
      Chapter <Ref Chap="Partitioned binary relations (PBRs)"/>) as defined in
      <Cite Key = "Martin2011aa"/>; and matrices over the following semirings:
      <List>
        <Item>
          the <E>Boolean semiring</E> <M>\{0, 1\}</M> where <M>0 + 0 = 0</M>,
          <M>0 + 1 = 1 + 1 = 1 + 0 = 1</M>, and <M>1\cdot 0 = 0 \cdot 0 = 0
            \cdot 1 = 0</M>
        </Item>
        <Item>
          finite fields;
        </Item>
        <Item>
          the <E>max-plus semiring</E> of natural numbers and negative
          infinity <M>\mathbb{N}\cup \{-\infty\}</M> with operations max and
          plus;
        </Item>
        <Item>
          the <E>min-plus semiring</E> of natural numbers and
          infinity <M>\mathbb{N}\cup \{\infty\}</M> with operations min and
          plus;
        </Item>
        <Item>
          the <E>tropical max-plus semiring</E> <M>\{-\infty, 0, 1,
            \ldots, t\}</M> for some threshold <M>t</M> with operations max
          and plus;
        </Item>
        <Item>
          the <E>tropical min-plus semiring</E> <M>\{0, 1,
            \ldots, t, \infty\}</M> for some threshold <M>t</M> with
          operations min and plus;
        </Item>
        <!-- <Item>
          the <E>projective max-plus semiring</E> ... TODO(later)
        </Item> -->
        <Item>
          the semiring <M>\mathbb{N}_{t, p} = \{0, 1,
            \ldots, t, t + 1, \ldots, t + p - 1\}</M> for some threshold
          <M>t</M> and period <M>p</M> under addition and multiplication
          modulo the congruence <M>t = t + p</M>.
        </Item>
      </List>
      (see Chapter <Ref Chap="Matrices over semirings"/>).<P/>

      The version of the Froidure-Pin Algorithm <Cite Key =
        "Froidure1997aa"/> written in C within the &SEMIGROUPS; package
      kernel module can be used to compute any other semigroup in &GAP; which
      satisfies <Ref Prop="CanUseGapFroidurePin"/>. In theory, any
      finite semigroup can be computed using this algorithm. However, the
      condition that the semigroup has satisfies <Ref
        Filt="CanUseGapFroidurePin"/> is imposed to avoid this method
      being used when it is inappropriate. If implementing a new type of
      semigroup in &GAP;, then simply do
<Log>InstallTrueMethod(CanUseGapFroidurePin,
                       MyNewSemigroupType);</Log>
      to make your new semigroup type <C>MyNewSemigroupType</C> use this
      version of the Froidure-Pin Algorithm.  To make this work efficiently it
      is necessary that a hash function is implemented for the elements of
      <C>MyNewSemigroupType</C>; more details will be included in a future
      edition of this manual.
      <P/>

      Mostly due to the way that &GAP; handles memory, this implementation is
      approximately 4 times slower than the implementation in
      &LIBSEMIGROUPS;.  This version of the Froidure-Pin Algorithm is
      included because it applies to a wider class of semigroups than those
      currently implemented in &LIBSEMIGROUPS; and it is more straightforward
      to extend the classes of semigroup to which it applies.
    </Subsection>

    <#Include Label = "CanUseFroidurePin">
  </Section>

  <Section Label = "Semigroups represented by generators">
    <Heading>Semigroups represented by generators</Heading>
    <#Include Label = "InverseMonoidByGenerators">
  </Section>

  <Section Label = "Options when creating semigroups">
    <Heading>Options when creating semigroups</Heading>

    When using any of the functions:
    <List>
      <Item><Ref Func = "InverseSemigroup"  BookName = "ref"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Func = "InverseMonoid" BookName = "ref"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Func = "Semigroup" BookName = "ref"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Func = "Monoid" BookName = "ref"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Meth = "SemigroupByGenerators" BookName = "ref"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Meth = "MonoidByGenerators" BookName = "ref"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Oper = "ClosureSemigroup"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Oper = "ClosureMonoid"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Oper = "ClosureInverseSemigroup"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Oper = "ClosureInverseMonoid"/>, </Item>
      <Item><Ref Func = "SemigroupIdeal"/></Item>
    </List>
    a record can be given as an optional final argument. The components of this
    record specify the values of certain options for the semigroup being
    created. A list of these options and their default values is given below.
    <P/>

    Assume that <A>S</A> is the semigroup created by one of the functions given
    above and that either: <A>S</A> is generated by a collection <A>gens</A>; or
    <A>S</A> is an ideal of such a semigroup.

    <List>
      <Mark><C>acting</C></Mark>
      <Item>
        this component should be <K>true</K> or <K>false</K>.

        Roughly speaking, there are two types of methods in the &SEMIGROUPS;
        package: those for semigroups which have to be fully enumerated, and
        those for semigroups that do not; see Section <Ref Sect =
          "Introduction"/>.
        In order for a semigroup to use the latter methods in
        <!-- the reference to IsActingSemigroup does not work -->
        &SEMIGROUPS; it must satisfy <Ref Filt="IsActingSemigroup"/>.  By
        default any semigroup or monoid of transformations, partial
        permutations, Rees 0-matrix elements, or bipartitions satisfies
        <C>IsActingSemigroup</C>.<P/>

        There are cases (such as when it is known <E>a priori</E> that the
        semigroup is &D;-trivial), when it might be preferable to use the
        methods that involve fully enumerating a semigroup. In other words, it
        might be desirable to disable the more sophisticated methods for acting
        semigroups.  If this is the case, then the value of this component can
        be set <K>false</K> when the semigroup is created.  Following this none
        of the special methods for acting semigroup will be used to compute
        anything about the semigroup.
      </Item>

      <Mark><C>regular</C></Mark>
      <Item>
        this component should be <K>true</K> or <K>false</K>. If it is known
        <E>a priori</E> that the semigroup <C>S</C> being created is a regular
        semigroup, then this component can be set to <K>true</K>. In this case,
        <C>S</C> knows it is a regular semigroup and can take advantage of the
        methods for regular semigroups in &SEMIGROUPS;. It is usually much more
        efficient to compute with a regular semigroup that to compute with a
        non-regular semigroup.<P/>

        If this option is set to <K>true</K> when the semigroup being defined
        is <B>not</B> regular, then the results might be unpredictable. <P/>

        The default value for this option is <K>false</K>.
      </Item>

      <Mark><C>hashlen</C></Mark>
      <Item>
        this component should be a positive integer, which roughly specifies the
        lengths of the hash tables used internally by &SEMIGROUPS;.  &SEMIGROUPS;
        uses hash tables in several fundamental methods.  The lengths of these
        tables are a compromise between performance and memory usage; larger
        tables provide better performance for large computations but use more
        memory.  Note that it is unlikely that you will need to specify this
        option unless you find that &GAP; runs out of memory unexpectedly or that
        the performance of &SEMIGROUPS; is poorer than expected. If you find that
        &GAP; runs out of memory unexpectedly, or you plan to do a large number
        of computations with relatively small semigroups (say with tens of
        thousands of elements), then you might consider setting <C>hashlen</C> to
        be less than the default value of <C>12517</C> for each of these
        semigroups.  If you find that the performance of &SEMIGROUPS; is
        unexpectedly poor, or you plan to do a computation with a very large
        semigroup (say, more than 10 million elements), then you might consider
        setting <C>hashlen</C> to be greater than the default value of
        <C>12517</C>. <P/>

        You might find it useful to set the info level of the info class
        <C>InfoOrb</C> to 2 or higher since this will indicate when hash tables
        used by &SEMIGROUPS; are being grown; see <Ref Oper = "SetInfoLevel"
        BookName = "ref"/>.
      </Item>

      <Mark><C>small</C></Mark> <Item>if this component is set to <K>true</K>,
        then &SEMIGROUPS; will compute a small subset of <A>gens</A> that
        generates <A>S</A> at the time that <A>S</A> is created. This will
        increase the amount of time required to create <A>S</A> substantially,
        but may decrease the amount of time required for subsequent
        calculations with <A>S</A>. If this component is set to <K>false</K>,
        then &SEMIGROUPS; will return the semigroup generated by <A>gens</A>
        without modifying <A>gens</A>. The default value for this component is
        <K>false</K>.<P/>

        This option is ignored when passed to <Ref Oper = "ClosureSemigroup"/>
        or <Ref Oper = "ClosureInverseSemigroup"/>.
    </Item>

    <Mark><C>cong_by_ker_trace_threshold</C></Mark>
    <Item>this should be a positive integer, which specifies a semigroup size.
        If <A>S</A> is a semigroup with inverse op, and <A>S</A> has a size
        greater than or equal to this threshold, then any congruence defined on
        it may use the "kernel and trace" method to perform calculations.  If
        its size is less than the threshold, then other methods will be used
        instead.  The "kernel and trace" method has better complexity than the
        generic method, but has large overheads which make it a poor choice for
        small semigroups.  The default value for this component is <C>10 ^
        5</C>.  See Section <Ref Sect = "Congruences on inverse semigroups"/>
        for more information about the "kernel and trace" method.
    </Item>

</List>

    <Example><![CDATA[
gap> S := Semigroup(Transformation([1, 2, 3, 3]),
>                   rec(hashlen := 100003, small := false));
<commutative transformation semigroup of degree 4 with 1 generator>]]></Example>

      The default values of the options described above are stored in a global
      variable named <Ref Var = "SEMIGROUPS.DefaultOptionsRec"/>. If you want to
      change the default values of these options for a single &GAP; session,
      then you can simply redefine the value in &GAP;. For example, to change
      the option <C>small</C> from the default value of <A>false</A> use:

<Log><![CDATA[
gap> SEMIGROUPS.DefaultOptionsRec.small := true;
true]]></Log>

    If you want to change the default values of the options stored in <Ref
      Var = "SEMIGROUPS.DefaultOptionsRec"/> for all &GAP; sessions, then you can
    edit these values in the file <F>semigroups-&VERSION;/gap/options.g</F>. <P/>

    <#Include Label = "SEMIGROUPS.DefaultOptionsRec">

   </Section>

  <Section>
    <Heading>Subsemigroups and supersemigroups</Heading>

    <#Include Label = "ClosureSemigroup">
    <#Include Label = "SubsemigroupByProperty">
    <#Include Label = "InverseSubsemigroupByProperty">

  </Section>

   <Section Label = "Changing the representation of a semigroup">
     <Heading>Changing the representation of a semigroup</Heading>

     The &SEMIGROUPS; package provides two convenient constructors
     <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismSemigroup"/> and
     <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismMonoid"/> for changing the representation of a given
     semigroup or monoid. These methods can be used to
     find an isomorphism from any semigroup to a semigroup of any other type,
     provided such an isomorphism exists. <P/>

     Note that at present neither <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismSemigroup"/> nor
     <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismMonoid"/> can be used to determine whether two
     given semigroups, or monoids, are isomorphic.<P/>

     Some methods for <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismSemigroup"/> and
     <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismMonoid"/> are based on
     methods for the &GAP; library operations:
     <List>
       <Item>
         <Ref Attr = "IsomorphismReesMatrixSemigroup" BookName = "ref"/>,
       </Item>
       <Item>
         <Ref Oper = "AntiIsomorphismTransformationSemigroup" BookName = "ref"/>,
       </Item>
       <Item>
         <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismTransformationSemigroup" BookName = "ref"/>
         and
         <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismTransformationMonoid" BookName = "ref"/>,
       </Item>
       <Item>
         <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismPartialPermSemigroup" BookName = "ref"/>
         and
         <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismPartialPermMonoid" BookName = "ref"/>,
       </Item>
       <Item>
         <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismFpSemigroup" BookName = "ref"/>
         and <C>IsomorphismFpMonoid</C>.
       </Item>
     </List>

     The operation <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismMonoid"/> can be used to return an
     isomorphism from a semigroup which is mathematically a monoid (but does not
     below to the category of monoids in &GAP; <Ref Filt = "IsMonoid" BookName
       = "ref"/>) into a monoid. This is the primary purpose of the operation
     <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismMonoid"/>. Either
     <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismSemigroup"/> or <Ref Oper = "IsomorphismMonoid"/>
     can be used to change the representation of a monoid, but only the latter
     is guaranteed to return an object in the category of monoids.
     <P/>

     <Example><![CDATA[
gap> S := Monoid(Transformation([1, 4, 6, 2, 5, 3, 7, 8, 9, 9]),
>                Transformation([6, 3, 2, 7, 5, 1, 8, 8, 9, 9]));;
gap> AsSemigroup(IsBooleanMatSemigroup, S);
<monoid of 10x10 boolean matrices with 2 generators>
gap> AsMonoid(IsBooleanMatMonoid, S);
<monoid of 10x10 boolean matrices with 2 generators>
gap> S := Semigroup(Transformation([1, 4, 6, 2, 5, 3, 7, 8, 9, 9]),
>                   Transformation([6, 3, 2, 7, 5, 1, 8, 8, 9, 9]));;
gap> AsSemigroup(IsBooleanMatSemigroup, S);
<semigroup of 10x10 boolean matrices with 2 generators>
gap> AsMonoid(IsBooleanMatMonoid, S);
<monoid of 8x8 boolean matrices with 2 generators>
gap> M := Monoid([
> Bipartition([[1, -3], [2, 3, 6], [4, 7, -6], [5, -8], [8, -4, -5],
>              [-1], [-2], [-7]]),
> Bipartition([[1, 3, -6], [2, -8], [4, 8, -1], [5], [6, -3, -4],
>              [7], [-2], [-5], [-7]]),
> Bipartition([[1, 2, 4, -3, -7, -8], [3, 5, 6, 8, -4, -6],
>              [7, -1, -2, -5]])]);;
gap> AsMonoid(IsPBRMonoid, M);
<pbr monoid of size 163, degree 163 with 3 generators>
gap> AsSemigroup(IsPBRSemigroup, M);
<pbr semigroup of size 163, degree 8 with 4 generators>]]></Example>

     There are some further methods in &SEMIGROUPS; for obtaining an isomorphism
     from a Rees matrix, or 0-matrix, semigroup to another such semigroup with
     particular properties; <Ref Attr = "RMSNormalization"/> and
     <Ref Attr = "RZMSNormalization"/>.

     <#Include Label = "IsomorphismSemigroup">
     <#Include Label = "IsomorphismMonoid">
     <#Include Label = "AsSemigroup">
     <#Include Label = "AsMonoid">
     <#Include Label = "IsomorphismPermGroup">
     <#Include Label = "RZMSNormalization">
     <#Include Label = "RMSNormalization">
     <#Include Label = "IsomorphismReesZeroMatrixSemigroup">

   </Section>

  <!--**********************************************************************-->
  <!--**********************************************************************-->

  <Section>
    <Heading>Random semigroups</Heading>

    <#Include Label = "RandomSemigroup">
  </Section>

  <!--**********************************************************************-->
  <!--**********************************************************************-->

</Chapter>
