<Chapter Label="The Semigroups package">
  <Heading>
    The &Semigroups; package
  </Heading>
  <Index Key="Semigroups">&Semigroups; package overview</Index>	

  <Section Label="Introduction">
    <Heading>
      Introduction
    </Heading>

    This is the manual for the &Semigroups; package for &GAP; version &VERSION;.
    &Semigroups; &VERSION; is a distant descendant of the  
    <URL Text="Monoid package for GAP 3">
      http://schmidt.nuigalway.ie/monoid/index.html</URL> by Goetz Pfeiffer,
    Steve A. Linton, Edmund F. Robertson, and Nik Ruskuc.<P/>

    &Semigroups; &VERSION; contains efficient methods for creating semigroups,
    monoids, inverse semigroups and their ideals, calculating their Green's
    structure, size, elements, group of units, minimal ideal, and testing
    membership, finding the inverses of a regular element, and factorizing
    elements over the generators, and much more; see Chapters <Ref
      Chap = "Creating semigroups and monoids"/>, <Ref Chap = "Ideals"/>, and  
    <Ref Chap = "Green's relations"/>. There
    are methods for testing if semigroups satisfy  particular
    properties, such as if they are regular, simple, inverse, completely regular,
    and a variety of further properties; see Chapter <Ref Chap="Green's
      relations"/>.<P/>

    There are methods for finding: congruences of semigroups, the normalizer of
    a semigroup in a permutation group (as given in <Cite
      Key="Araujo2010aa"/>), the maximal subsemigroups of a finite semigroup
    (based on  <Cite Key="Graham1968aa"/>), smaller degree partial permutation
    representations (based on <Cite Key="Schein1992aa"/>) and the character
    table of an inverse semigroup.  There are functions for producing pictures
    of the Green's structure of a semigroup, and for drawing graphical
    representations of the elements of certain semigroups; see Chapter <Ref
      Sect="The Grape package"/>. <P/>

    Many standard examples of semigroups and classes of semigroups are provided;
    see Section <Ref Sect="Standard examples"/>.  &Semigroups; also provides
    functions to read and write collections of transformations, partial
    permutations, and bipartitions to a file; see <Ref Func="ReadGenerators"/>
    and <Ref Func="WriteGenerators"/>.<P/>

    There are functions in &Semigroups; to define and manipulate free
    inverse semigroups and free bands; this part of the package was written
    by Julius Jonu&#353;as; see Chapters <Ref Chap="Free inverse semigroups"/>
    and <Ref Chap="Free bands"/>.
    <P/>

    There are three fundamental types of algorithms in the &Semigroups; package,
    those for semigroups of:
    <Enum> 
      <Item>
        transformations, partial permutations, bipartitions, and subsemigroups
        of regular Rees 0-matrix semigroups over groups. When applied to
        semigroups with large
        subgroups these are the most efficient methods in the &Semigroups;
        package. For example, the complexity of computing, say, the size of a
        transformation semigroup that happens to be a group, is the same as the
        complexity of the Schreier-Sims Algorithm (polynomial in the number of
        points acted on by the transformations) for a permutation group. <P/>

        The algorithms of this type are described in <Cite
          Key="Mitchell2015aa"/>. In theory, these algorithms can be applied to
        compute any subsemigroup of a regular semigroup.  For details of how to
        extend &Semigroups; see <Ref Chap="Extending the package"/>.  
        We refer to semigroups to which the algorithms in <Cite
          Key="Mitchell2015aa"/> can be applied as <E>acting semigroups</E>.
        See Section <Ref Sect="Acting Semigroups"/> for further details.
      </Item>

      <Item>
        partitioned binary relations as defined in <Cite Key="Mazorchuk20????"/>, and 
        matrices over the following semirings:
        <List>
          <Item> 
            the <E>Boolean semiring</E> <M>\{0,1\}</M> where <M>0 + 0 = 0</M>,
            <M>0 + 1 = 1 + 1 = 1 + 0 = 1</M>, and <M>1\cdot 0 = 0 \cdot 0 = 0
              \cdot 1 = 0</M>
          </Item>
          <Item> 
            fields of prime order;
          </Item>
          <Item> 
            the <E>max-plus semiring</E> of natural numbers and negative
            infinity <M>\mathbb{N}\cup \{-\infty\}</M> with operations max and
            plus;
          </Item>
          <Item> 
            the <E>min-plus semiring</E> of natural numbers and
            infinity <M>\mathbb{N}\cup \{\infty\}</M> with operations min and
            plus;
          </Item>
          <Item> 
            the <E>tropical max-plus semiring</E> <M>\{-\infty, 0, 1,
              \ldots, t\}</M> for some threshold <M>t</M> with operations max
            and plus;
          </Item>
          <Item> 
            the <E>tropical min-plus semiring</E> <M>\{0, 1,
              \ldots, t, \infty\}</M> for some threshold <M>t</M> with
            operations min and plus;
          </Item>
          <Item> 
            the tropical min-plus semiring <M>\mathbb{N}_{t,p} = \{0, 1,
              \ldots, t, t + 1, \ldots, t + p - 1\}</M> for some threshold <M>t</M> 
            and period <M>p</M> under addition and mutliplication modulo the congruence 
            <M>t = t + p</M>.
          </Item>
        </List>
        A version of the Froidure-Pin Algorithm <Cite Key="Froidure1997aa"/>
        (written in C++) is used to compute semigroups of these types. The
        implementation in &Semigroups; performs at least as well as the C
        programme <Cite Key="Pin2009aa"/> by Jean-Eric Pin. This algorithm out
        performs the algorithms for acting semigroups when applied to
        semigroups with small (trivial) subgroups, and is also used for
        semigroups to which the algorithms described in <Cite
          Key="Mitchell2015aa"/> do not apply. It is possible to specify which
        methods should be applied to a given semigroup; see Section
        <Ref Sect="Options when creating semigroups"/>.
      </Item>

      <Item>
        any other semigroup in &GAP;. A version of the Froidure-Pin Algorithm
        <Cite Key="Froidure1997aa"/> (written in &GAP; kernel code) is used to
        compute semigroups of this type. Mostly due to the way that &GAP;
        handles memory, this implementation is approximately 4 times slower
        than the C++ implementation when applied to semigroups of the types
        given in <E>2.</E> However, this implementation has the advantage that
        it can be applied to any semigroup defined in &GAP;.
      </Item>
    </Enum>

    <B>Minor note of caution</B>: &Semigroups; contains different methods for some
    &GAP; library functions, and so you might notice that &GAP; behaves
    differently when &Semigroups; is loaded.  For more details about semigroups
    in &GAP; or Green's relations in particular, see <Ref Sect="Semigroups"
      BookName="ref"/> or <Ref Sect="Green's Relations" BookName="ref"/>.<P/>

    This manual is organised as follows:


    If you find a bug or an issue with the package, then report this using the
    <URL Text="issue
      tracker">http://bitbucket.org/james-d-mitchell/semigroups/issues</URL>.

  </Section>

</Chapter>
